Finding Aid for Democratic Party of Michigan records, 1932-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Democratic Party of Michigan records 1932-2008, 1950-1994
Democratic Party (Mich.)
1 film reels
97 linear feet (in 99 boxes)
85686 Bt 2
Files of state chairs, Neil Staebler, John J. Collins, Zolton Ferency, Sander Levin, James McNeely, Morley Winograd, Olivia Maynard, Richard Wiener, F. Thomas LeWand, and Gary Corbin; files of deputy state chair, Billie S. Farnum, vice chairs Adelaide Hart and Olivia Maynard, and vice chair Robert Mitchell; files relating to state constitutional convention, and to state and national political campaigns, since 1950; sound recordings and visual materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group came from the Lansing headquarters of the Democratic Party of Michigan (donor no. 4474 ) in multiple accessions beginning in 1967.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Democratic Party of Michigan is a non-profit organization affiliated with the Democratic National Committee, and its State Chairman is a member of the Association of State Democratic chairs. The group is dedicated to supporting Democratic candidates for public office in the state of Michigan, promoting the party in Michigan, and fielding the concerns of Michigan citizens as part of their effort to affect legislative change.
Although the Democratic Party State Central Committee has been in Michigan since the mid-19th century, it wasn't until the late 1940s that it was rejuvenated and strengthened. Until that time there were only small "paper groups" of isolated Democratic enthusiasts, with the exceptions of Wayne County and the western Upper Peninsula where more substantial committees had organized. At the time, the Democratic Party represented a more liberal perspective, including protest groups, new immigrants, and fledgling unions. With the 1948 election of Democrat G. Mennen Williams, the party began to gain a foothold in Michigan politics, and the Democratic Party State Central Committee (DPSCC) began to develop.
In 1949 the group held its Spring Convention and elected Chairman Hicks Griffiths and Vice Chairman Margaret Cotsikas. Its first major project was the revitalization of the annual Jefferson-Jackson Dinner. Attended by 1200 people at the Detroit Masonic Temple, the guest speaker was Senator Hubert Humphrey.
With the success of the "Jeff-Jack" Dinner and a morale boost for the party, the DPSCC adopted the slogan "A candidate for every office, a challenger in every polling place and a worker in every precinct." They followed up the slogan with manuals on challenging and precinct work and through the development of county-level, grassroots organizations. In the early 1950s, the DPSCC set a budget and opened itself to public scrutiny. The group established field representatives, county committees, and sub-committees, and the operation became year-round rather than solely at the time of elections. The group enjoyed increased membership, improved fund-raising, diversified participation, and a reputation for "honest politics." They established financial drives, founded the Young Democrats, worked to further integrate women into the party, and established the monthly publication Michigan Democrat.
In 1965, under the second term of State Chairman Zolton Ferency, the group purchased a building in Lansing for their permanent headquarters. It was dedicated the John F. Kennedy House in October 1965, and the dedication address was given by Senator Edward (Ted) Kennedy of Massachusetts.
The Democratic Party of Michigan suffered financial and developmental difficulties in the early 1990s after the surprising defeat of Governor James Blanchard by Republican John Engler. (Some records in the collection hint that the party has followed a similar cycle throughout its history.) As a result, much of 1991 and 1992, under the leadership of State Chairman Gary Corbin, was spent trying to rebuild the party through financial support, increased membership, speaking events, and direct communication via mail with citizens who wrote the party to express their concerns. One of the primary issues of concern for the party and for citizens was Governor Engler's budget for Michigan, including sharp cuts in social services for the poor and elderly and concerns regarding education and taxation.
The records of the Democratic Party of Michigan have come to the library in several accessions beginning in 1967 and periodically thereafter. The record group is comprised of files mainly from the Lansing office of the Democratic Party of Michigan. The files are of the officers of the party: state chair, vice chair, deputy chair, and secretary among others. As might be expected, the records relate to the day-to-day operation of the party, the management of political campaigns (i.e. selecting candidates, defining issues, raising funds, getting out the vote, etc.). In addition, much of the records concern the state organization's relationship with the National Democratic Party and its participation in the national convention to select a presidential nominee. Because of inconsistencies in how files were maintained and used, the files of one party officer might also include materials of his / her predecessor. Thus the researcher should be examine the entire finding aid for material on any given topic or time period.
The records of the Democratic Party of Michigan has been arranged into the following series: (1) Earlier records, prior to 1965; (2) State Chair, Democratic State Central Committee files; (3) Other Party Officers; (4) Headquarters files; (5) Detroit Office Files; (6) Topical Files; (7) State Central Committee Meeting Minutes; (8) State and National Convention files; (9) Appeals Committee; (10) Publications and miscellaneous; (11) Visual Materials; (12) Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Democratic Party (Mich.); Democratic Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Elections--Michigan--1952.; Elections--Michigan--1958.; Elections--Michigan--1960.; Elections--Michigan--1962.; Elections--Michigan--1968.; Elections--Michigan--1970.; Elections--Michigan--1972.; Elections--Michigan--1974.; Elections--Michigan--1976.; Elections--Michigan--1980.; Elections--Michigan--1984.; Elections--Michigan--1988.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Presidents--United States--Election--1968.; Presidents--United States--Election--1976.; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Governors--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African Americans--Political life.; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Democratic Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Mondale, Walter F., 1928-; Parades and processions.; Political conventions.; Political elections.; Seals.; Voting.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Women--Political life.; Young, Coleman A.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Democratic Party (Mich.); Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Elections--United States--1968.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Contributors - Sound Recordings:
Colburn, Sherwood.; Crandall, Norman.; Dingell, John D.; Downs, Tom, 1916-; Farnum, Billie S. (Billie Sunday), 1916-; Ferency, Zolton A., 1922-1993; Ford, William D.; Gillis, Joseph A., 1895-; Hare, James M. (James McNeil), 1910-1980; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986.; Hart, Adelaide, 1900-; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Jeffrey, Mildred, 1911-2004.; Karoub, James, 1929-1994.; Keith, Damon J. (Damon Jerome), 1922-; McNamara, Patrick Vincent, 1894-1966.; Nathanson, Ben, 1915-; Nedzi, Lucien, 1925-; O'Hara, James G.; Patrick, William.; Rostow, W. W. (Walt Whitman), 1916-2003; Staebler, Neil, 1905-2000; Stevens, Roy.; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.; Towner, Charles R., 1927-
Contributors - Papers
Corbin, Gary.; LeWand, F. Thomas.; Wiener, Richard.; Collins, John J. (John Joseph), 1935-; Farnum, Billie S. (Billie Sunday), 1916-; Ferency, Zolton A., 1922-1993; Hart, Adelaide, 1900-; Knox, Patti.; Levin, Sander, 1931-; McNeely, James, 1930-; Maynard, Olivia.; Mitchell, Robert.; Staebler, Neil, 1905-2000; Winograd, Morley.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Earlier records, prior to 1965
  The Earlier Records series consists of records from approximately 1949 to 1964 during the chairmanship of Neil Staebler, John J. Collins and deputy chair Billie S. Farnum. There is also a scattering of miscellaneous materials from the nineteenth century and the 1930s. Of some interest are files relating to the party's participation in the Democratic National Conventions of 1956 and 1960. Although the files are somewhat sparse prior to 1964, this may be accounted for because some important Democratic Party officials maintained their own files apart from the Party's office files. Fortunately many of these individuals also donated their records to the Bentley Historical Library. These include Neil Staebler, Margaret Price, and John J. Collins.
  - Miscellaneous
    - Statement of expenditures of Democratic Party in Michigan (early 19th century) (Box 1)
    - Michigan Federation of Democratic Women's Clubs circa 1934, 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - Proposal for handling publicity and advertising for Democratic state campaign circa 1932 (Box 1)
    - Party organization 1932-1933 (arranged by county) (Box 1)
    - Minutes of State Central Committee 1949-1952 (Box 1)
    - Caucus reports of the Spring State Party convention 1949 (Box 1)
  - Political files 1950-1964
    - 1950
      - Campaign bulletins (Box 1)
      - Financial miscellanea (Box 1)
      - Form letters (Box 1)
      - Radio advertising (Box 1)
      - Negro vote (Box 1)
      - County finance committees (Box 1)
      - Campaign literature (Box 1)
      - Campaign miscellanea (Box 1)
      - County canvas (Box 1)
      - Sidney Woolner assessment of campaign (Box 1)
    - 1951
      - Ann Arbor Office files (Box 1)
      - Finance director's files (Box 1)
      - Financial miscellanea (Box 1)
      - Inaugural (Box 1)
      - Spring State Convention, Grand Rapids 1951 (Box 1)
      - April 2nd Spring Election
        - Campaign bulletins and form letters (Box 1)
        - Campaign miscellanea (Box 1)
      - State Central Committee
        - Form letters (Box 1)
        - Mackinac Island Conference August 1951 (Box 1)
        - District meetings (Box 1)
        - Financial papers (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1952
      - Form letters (Box 1)
      - Keynote Day dinner February 1952 (Box 1)
      - Michigan Federation of Democratic Women (Box 1)
      - County committee files (Box 1)
      - State Democratic Convention August 1952 (Box 1)
      - Election campaign November 1952 (Box 1)
      - Financial papers (Box 1)
      - Blair Moody senatorial campaign (Box 1)
    - 1954
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - 1955
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - 1956
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - National Convention 1956 (Chicago) (Box 1)
      - Michigan Delegation (Box 1)
      - Miscellanea (Box 1)
      - Pre-convention preparations (Box 1)
      - Television and press relations (Box 1)
    - 1957
      - Spring State Convention, Grand Rapids (Box 2)
      - Spring Election
        - Press releases (Box 2)
        - John C. Mackie campaign for Highway Commissioner (Box 2)
        - Lynn Bartlett campaign for State Superintendent of Education (Box 2)
        - Campaign miscellanea (Box 2)
        - Assessment of campaign (Box 2)
        - Legislative Conference Planning Committee (Box 2)
        - Republican Party resolutions February 1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958
      - Legislative Liaison Committee "Legislative Kit" (Box 2)
      - Democratic Campaign Directory 1958-1959 (Box 2)
      - State convention, Grand Rapids August 1958 (Box 3)
      - Form letters (Box 3)
      - Press releases (Box 3)
      - Campaign correspondence (Box 3)
      - Radio advertising (Box 3)
      - "Get-Out-the-Vote" drive (Box 3)
      - Election Procedure (Box 3)
      - Candidate biographies (Box 3)
      - Campaign miscellanea (Box 3)
      - Registration campaign (Box 3)
      - Congressional campaign (Box 3)
      - State Legislative campaign, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - John B. Swainson campaign for Lt. Governor (Box 3)
      - Philip A. Hart campaign for U.S. Senator, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Republican campaign (Box 3)
      - Constitutional convention referendum (Box 3)
      - Biographies of party workers (Box 3)
      - Election statistics (Box 3)
    - 1959
      - Miscellaneous (largely Spring Election) (Box 3)
      - State Central Committee (Box 3)
    - 1960
      - General (Box 3)
      - State Central Committee (Box 3)
      - Legislative Liaison Committee "Legislative Kit" (Box 3)
      - Biographies of candidates (Box 3)
      - Business and Professional Committee (Box 3)
      - Otis Smith schedules and meetings, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Paul Adams schedules and meetings, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Sanford Brown schedules and meetings, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Philip Hart schedules and meetings (Box 3)
      - Theodore Souris schedules and meetings (Box 3)
      - James Hare schedules and meetings, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Pat McNamara campaign for U.S. Senator (Box 3)
      - Candidates' wives schedules and meetings, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Schedules and meetings, general, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Kennedy Tour of State October 1960 (Box 3)
      - Religious Issue (Box 3)
      - Democratic Midwest Conference, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Pre-Spring Convention Platform Committee (Box 4)
      - Spring Convention, Grand Rapids (Box 4)
      - Program (Box 4)
      - Platform resolutions, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Speeches (Box 4)
      - District Caucus Reports (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - National Convention 1960 (Los Angeles) (Box 4)
      - Appraisals (Box 4)
      - Biographical information (Box 4)
      - General information or Michigan Delegation (Box 4)
      - Headquarters (Box 4)
      - Johnson, Lyndon: paper by J. Oliver Hall on reaction of Michigan delegation to the nomination of Lyndon Johnson for vice-president (Box 4)
      - Platform (Box 4)
      - Pre-convention material, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Press coverage (Box 4)
      - Proposals for changes in convention procedures (Box 4)
      - Volunteer help (Box 4)
    - 1961
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - 1962
      - Campaign Handbook (Box 4)
      - Directory 1961-1962 (Box 4)
      - Precincts and Registration by Counties (Box 4)
      - Precinct results (Box 4)
      - John B. Swainson campaign for Governor (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Political files 1963
      - Democratic Spring Campaign Directory (Box 4)
    - 1964
      - Platform (Box 4)
      - Candidates (Box 4)
      - Democratic Legislative Program (Box 4)
      - Voting statistics 1946-1964 (Box 4)
      - Election Statistics (Box 4)
      - Election Statistics (notebook) (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Constitutional Convention Files
    - Papers 1957-1959 (Box 5)
    - Papers 1960 (Box 5)
    - Papers 1961 (Box 5)
    - Clippings 1961 (Box 5)
    - General materials for Democratic delegates (Box 5)
    - Delegate lists, clippings, etc., 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Reapportionment-clippings, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Republican statements (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - County Data file
    - September 1961, 13 folders (Box 5)
      (Arranged alphabetically by county (excludes larger counties); each folder contains economical, political, and other demographic information)
  - Clipping file
    - Bagwell, Paul D. (Box 5)
    - Budget
      - 1957-1958 (Box 5)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 5)
      - 1961 (Box 5)
    - Business Climate
      - 1957 (Box 6)
      - 1958 (Box 6)
      - 1959 (Box 6)
      - 1960 (Box 6)
    - Cash Crisis 1959, 2 folders (Box 6)
      (See also Taxation)
    - Cash Crisis-Trust Fund (Box 6)
    - Citizens Alliance to Build Michigan 1958 (Box 6)
    - Civil Rights 1959 (Box 6)
    - Conservation 1958-1959 (Box 6)
    - Democratic Midwest Conference 1960 (Box 6)
    - Economy
      - General 1957-1960, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Automobile Industry 1958 (Box 6)
    - Education 1958-1960 (Box 6)
    - Election of 1958
      - General, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Congressional campaign (Box 6)
      - Republican campaign (Box 6)
      - National campaign (Box 7)
      - Williams campaign for governor (Box 7)
    - Highways 1958-1960 (Box 7)
    - Hoffa, James R. (Box 7)
    - Legislature
      - 1958 (Box 7)
      - 1959 (Box 7)
      - 1960 (Box 7)
      - 1962 (Box 7)
    - Mental Health
      - 1958-1960, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - School aid 1958-1960 (Box 7)
    - Swainson, John B.
      - 1959-1960 (Box 7)
      - 1961, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 1962 (Box 7)
      - Operation Abolition (Box 7)
    - Taxation
      (see also Cash Crisis)
      - General, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Business Tax (Box 7)
      - Conlin Package (Box 8)
      - Equalization (Box 8)
      - Tax fight, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Income Tax (Box 8)
      - Intangibles Tax (Box 8)
      - Sales Tax (Box 8)
      - Use Tax (Box 8)
    - Unemployment
      - General, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Unemployment compensation
      - Temporary unemployment compensation (Box 8)
      - Ford-Canton strike (Box 8)
    - Welfare (Box 8)
- State Chair, Democratic State Central Committee files
  The largest series in the Democratic Party record group are the files of the individual chairs of the State Central Committee. The names of these chairs are Zolton Ferency (1963-1968), Sander Levin (1968-1969), James McNeely (1969-1973), Morley Winograd (1973-1979), Richard Wiener (1983-1989), F. Thomas Lewand (1989-1991), and Gary Corbin (1991-1996). The records of Olivia Maynard when she served as state chair (1979-1983) will be found throughout the Headquarters and Topical Files. There is also a separately cataloged collection of Olivia Maynard personal papers. Although there are variations in the quantity and content of the records of each chair, there is usually documentation of the administration of the State Central Committee office, the management of the state conventions, the oversight of the various state elections, and the Party's activities at the national convention and during presidential campaigns. Another value of these files is for their documentation of the issues of the day.
  - Deputy State Chairman (Billie S. Farnum)/State Chairman (John J. Collins)
    - Topical files 1961-1962
      - Advisory Board (Box 8)
      - Alger County (Box 8)
      - Allegan County, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Antrim County (Box 8)
      - Barry County (Box 8)
      - Bay County (Box 8)
      - Benzie County (Box 8)
      - Berrien County (Box 8)
      - Branch County (Box 8)
      - Branch Manager Appointments (Box 8)
      - Business and Professional Association (Box 8)
      - Calhoun County (Box 8)
      - Cass County (Box 8)
      - Cheboygan County (Box 8)
      - Citizenship Clearing House (Box 8)
      - Civil Service Commission (Box 8)
      - Clare County (Box 8)
      - Clifford, Richard (Box 8)
      - Clinton County (Box 9)
      - Collector of Custom (Box 9)
      - Con-Con candidates (Box 9)
      - Con-Con (general), 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Democratic State Central Committee (Box 9)
      - Dollars for Democrats (Box 9)
      - Eaton County (Box 9)
      - Emmet County (Box 9)
      - Federal Appointments (Requests for) (Box 9)
      - Field Staff Reports (Box 9)
      - Finance Correspondence (Box 9)
      - Fox, Mary (Box 9)
      - Genesee County (Box 9)
      - Gogebic County (Box 9)
      - Goodwin, W.O. (Box 9)
      - Grand Traverse County (Box 9)
      - Gratiot County (Box 9)
      - Housing and Metropolitan Affairs Advisory Committee (Box 9)
      - Huron County (Box 9)
      - Inaugural (Box 9)
      - Ingham County (Box 9)
      - Iosco County (Box 9)
      - Iron County (Box 9)
      - Isabella County (Box 9)
      - Jeffrey, Mildred (Box 9)
      - Kennedy campaign 1960 (Box 9)
      - Lake County (Box 9)
      - Lapeer County (Box 9)
      - Leelanau County (Box 9)
      - Lenawee County (Box 9)
      - Mackinac County (Box 9)
      - Madison Heights Democratic Club (Box 9)
      - Maniscalco, Ann (reports and recommendations) (Box 9)
      - McNamara, Sen. Patrick (Box 9)
      - Mecosta County (Box 9)
      - Membership Drive (Box 9)
      - Midland County (Box 9)
      - Midwest Conference (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
      - National Committee (Box 9)
      - Newaygo County (Box 9)
      - Oakland County [also Newaygo County] (Box 9)
      - Ogemaw County (Box 9)
      - "Operation Support" (Box 9)
      - Osceola County (Box 9)
      - Otsego County (Box 9)
      - Ottawa County (Box 9)
      - Party Leaderships (Box 9)
      - Patronage-appointments (Box 9)
      - Patronage-correspondence (Box 9)
      - Phillips, Harriett (Box 9)
      - Presque Isle County (Box 9)
      - Regional meetings (Box 9)
      - Roller, Murnie (Box 9)
      - Saginaw County (Box 9)
      - St. Clair County (Box 9)
      - St. Joseph County (Box 9)
      - Sanilac County (Box 9)
      - Schoolcraft County (Box 9)
      - Speaker's Bureau, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Staebler, Neil (Box 9)
      - Thurber, Donald (Box 9)
      - Tuscola County (Box 9)
      - Washtenaw County (Box 9)
      - Wayne County (Box 9)
      - Wexford County (Box 9)
      - Young Democrats (Box 9)
    - Chronological file (Billie S. Farnum)
      - April 1961 (Box 9)
      - May 1961 (Box 9)
      - June 1961 (Box 9)
      - July 1961 (Box 9)
      - August 1961 (Box 9)
      - September 1961 (Box 9)
      - October 1961 (Box 9)
    - Chronological file (John J. Collins)
      - June 1961 (Box 9)
      - July 1961 (Box 9)
      - August 1961 (Box 9)
      - September 1961 (Box 9)
      - October 1961 (Box 9)
  - State Chairman (Zolton Ferency)
    - Topical file 1963-1967
      - Apportionment
        (see also Supreme Court Apportionment Suit)
        - 1963 candidates for Legislative Apportionment Commission (Box 10)
        - 1963-1964 Legislative Apportionment Commission (Box 10)
        - 1964 Legislative Apportionment Commission, 3 folders (Box 10)
        - 1964 apportionment and district plan of the House of Representatives (Box 10)
        - 1965 legislative (Box 10)
        - 1966 apportionment (Box 10)
        - 1966 task force on apportionment (Box 10)
      - Communication, party mass 1963 (Box 10)
      - Congressional redistricting 1963-1964 (Box 10)
      - Dollars for democrats 1966 (Box 10)
      - Fair share 1965 (Box 10)
      - Forward Michigan dinner 1966 (Box 10)
      - Gala or spectacular affair 1963 (Box 10)
      - Hubert H. Humphrey Dinner 1966 (Box 10)
      - John F. Kennedy House (D.S.C.C. HQ's)
        - 1965-1966 Fund drive correspondence (Box 10)
        - 1965 Fund reports (Box 10)
        - 1965 Dedication information, correspondence (Box 10)
        - 1966-1967 General memos and correspondence (Box 10)
        - 1967 contributions (Box 10)
        - 1967 Pledges (Box 10)
        - 1967 Zolton Ferency's list (Box 10)
      - Robert Lewis-Lewis and Lewis Agency (suit against Neil Staebler) 1964 (Box 10)
      - Legislative Information For Teamwork (L.I.F.T.), Correspondence, newsletters 1965-1966 (Box 10)
      - Membership Drive
        - 1965 (Box 10)
        - 1966 (Box 10)
        - 1967, 2 folders (Box 10)